Finding Aid for David S. Evans papers, 1954-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David S. Evans papers 1954-1979
Evans, David S.
1 linear foot.
921077 Aa 2
Methodist minister. Working files detailing his opposition to ballot proposals that would have legalized charity gambling in 1954 and 1956; also files concerning his opposition to a parochiaid proposal in 1970.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dr. David S. Evans (donor no. 7963 ) donated this collection on August 6, 1991.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
On February 1, 1954, the Michigan Council of Churches stated their position in regard to a bill pending in the Michigan Senate that would allow charity gambling. Dr. David S. Evans, Methodist minister in Okemos, Michigan (later in Battle Creek and then in Hillsdale, Michigan), became active in a drive to defeat the proposal, a drive already backed by other members of the Michigan Council of Churches. His work helped to defeat Proposal 4 on the Michigan Ballot on Nov. 2, 1954, that would have allowed charity gambling.
Dr. Evans acted as secretary for the "Life and Work" committee for the Methodist Church. His papers include correspondence from April 23, 1954 to April 27, 1956. He served as secretary on the Board of Social and Economic Relations for the Michigan Council of Churches. Plans and minutes of meetings from 1952 to 1956 are included.
From April 20 to August 6, 1956, Dr. Evans worked to defeat a petition that would have put charity bingo on the ballot. Some of the papers documenting his opposition to the charity bingo petition are included.
From early 1969 to the November election of 1970, Dr. Evans helped to defeat a parochiaid proposal on the Michigan ballot. During that time he coordinated efforts of church groups and educational organizations to defeat the proposal. In addition to documenting his opposition to the proposal, his papers also include letters and press clippings from those who backed the proposal. Also included are documents and correspondence relating to an appeal to the U.S. Supreme Court in March 1971 to overturn the results of the Michigan ballot. The appeal failed.
From 1977 to 1979 Dr. Evans was active in the Council About Parochiaid. He helped to defeat a proposal on the 1978 ballot in Michigan that would have allowed vouchers for private schools.
The David Evans papers document the processes used by church and educational organizations in Michigan to educate and mobilize the public on behalf of ballot proposals. The collection consists of the working files of Dr. David Evans and relates to the two proposals, the first in the 1950s that would have allowed charity gambling and the second in the period of 1968 to 1971 which would have allowed the expenditure of public money on parochial schools. Documents in the collection include minutes, reports, background information, clippings, press releases, and related materials.
Subjects:
Church schools--Michigan--Finance.; Clergy--Michigan.; Council about Parochiaid.; Elections--Michigan--1954.; Elections--Michigan--1970.; Evans, David S.; Gambling.; Methodist Church (U.S.)--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Parochiaid.; Government aid to private schools--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
- Working files: anti-gambling, anti-parochiaid, etc.
  - Anti-gambling campaign, 1949-March 21, 1951
    - Background (Box 1)
    - Background in Michigan (Box 1)
    - Plans and Results: February 1-September 30, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Plans and Results: October 1, 1954-March 21, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1954 (Box 1)
  - "Life and Work" Committee, Michigan Council of Churches, April 23, 1954-April 27, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Board of Social and Economic Relations, Michigan Council of Churches, (minutes), 1952-1956 (Box 1)
  - Anti-Bingo Campaign, September, 1955-August 6, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Anti-Parochiaid Campaign, 1968-March 3, 1971
    - Council Against Parochiaid, (flyer), 1968-December 18, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Press Clippings (Box 1)
    - Council Against Parochiaid, January 21-April 30, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Expense Account Sheets, March 13-June 27, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, May 1-December 19, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Action in Michigan Court of Appeals, March 24-September 8, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Opposition (Box 1)
    - Press Releases, October 12-November 2, 1970 (Box 1)
    - News Clippings, May 13-November 1, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Post-election miscellaneous; include appeal from opposition; appeal to U.S. Supreme Court, December 1, 1970 preparation for court appearance; hearing at Supreme Court, March 23, 1971 reactions to ruling, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Council About Parochiaid (Voucheraid)
    - September 21, 1977-March 8, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Press Clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Kit Clardy, letters, etc., 1954 (Box 1)